<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc1034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2181 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2181.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2606 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2606.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7816 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7816.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8020 SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8020.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis SYSTEM
"http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis.xml">
]>
<rfc docName="draft-bortzmeyer-dns-rfc-bis-00-BETA"
     category="std" ipr="trust200902">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="DNS RFC bis">New versions of the base DNS RFCs</title>
<author fullname="Stephane Bortzmeyer" initials="S." surname="Bortzmeyer">
<organization>AFNIC</organization>
<address><postal><street>1, rue Stephenson</street><code>78180</code><city>Montigny-le-Bretonneux</city><country>France</country></postal> <phone>+33 1 39 30 83 46</phone><email>bortzmeyer+ietf@nic.fr</email><uri>http://www.afnic.fr/</uri></address>
</author>
<date month="TODO" year="TODO"/>
<workgroup>Individual</workgroup>
<abstract>
  <t>This document describes the project to update the base DNS RFCs
with new and up-to-date documents. It describes the goal, the method
and the main choices. The RFC-bis documents themselves are separate
documents, not yet published.</t>
  <t>It is not intended to be published as a RFC.</t>
<t>REMOVE BEFORE PUBLICATION: this document should be discussed in the
IETF DNSOP group, through its mailing list, as long as there is no
chartered working group for this project. The
source of the document, as well as a list of open issues, is currently
kept <eref
target="https://github.com/bortzmeyer/rfc-dns">at Github</eref>.</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction and background">
    <t>The DNS protocol (<xref
    target="RFC1034"/>, <xref
    target="RFC1035"/>) is a serious challenge to every implementer or
    to every engineer who tries to understand it from the reference
    RFCs. The official standards are very old (almost twenty years),
    ambiguous on many things, and sometimes obsolete. Both the
    concepts and the terminology have changed a lot since 1987.</t>
    <t>Someone who wants to understand the "official" DNS today has to
    read not only these official RFCs but also several others that
    update, patch or precise some aspects of the DNS. This is hardly a
    satisfying state for a protocol which is so critical. For
    instance, it allows bad faith actors to have broken name servers,
    while claiming to be compliant.</t>
    <t>Other old protocols managed to consolidate the various
    documents in a recent set of documents, giving the protocol a
    solid and modern specification. This is the case with SMTP (<xref
    target="RFC5321"/>), the Internet Message Format (<xref
    target="RFC5322"/>) and HTTP (<xref target="RFC7230"/> and
    friends). It is time to do the same for the DNS.</t>
    <t>The goal is therefore to produce two documents, 1034-bis and 1035-bis which will
      obsolete <xref target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/>,
      as well as the various RFCs that patch them (such as <xref
      target="RFC2181"/>, <xref target="RFC7766"/> or <xref target="RFC8020"/>).</t>
     <t>The process is not expected to be an easy or a fast one, it
      will probably last several years.</t>
    <t>The charter of the DNSOP working group<!--  &I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis;
    https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/dnsop/charter/ -->, in force at
    the time of this draft, does not allow such a big change in the
    base documents of the DNS. Working on this project will probably require a
    rechartering of the group, or the creation of a new working
    group. It could be a BoF at IETF 99 in Prague.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="choices" title="The choices">
    <t>Here are the proposed choices for the project:
    <list>
      <t>No change in the protocol (like it was done for the SMTP or
      HTTP RFC revisions). Software which was compliant should stay
      compliant. This goal is not completely realistic: ambiguity in
      original RFCs (for instance for ENTs) may result in
      difficulties.</t>
      <t>We use the RFCs on DNS which are on the Standards track.</t>
      <t>Use <xref target="RFC2119"/> and <xref target="RFC2606"/>.</t>
      <t>DNSSEC will be left alone (<xref target="RFC4034"/> and
      friends are fine).</t>
      <t>The terminology will be based on <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis"/>.</t>
      <t>The goal of the new RFCs will be to describe the protocol,
      not the operational practices. Best practices like TODO
      Wallström draft are out of scope.</t>
    </list></t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="open" title="Open questions">
    <t>Here are some issues to address before starting the real work:
    <list>
      <t>Should we use the definition of domain names in <xref target="I-D.lewis-domain-names"/>?</t>
      <t>Some RFCs may be integrated in the new RFCs, or could be left
      alone because they are not mandatory for understanding the
      DNS but they are so widely useful that one could argue they are
      part of the base DNS. This is the case with <xref
      target="RFC1996"/> or <xref target="RFC2845"/>.</t>
      <t>Should we integrate <xref target="RFC7816"/> (currently experimental)?</t>
    </list></t>
  </section>
  
<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>None.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>None.</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>Obvsiously to Paul Mockapetris, for inventing the DNS, and writing
the current RFCs.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title='Normative References'>
  &rfc1034;
  &rfc1035;
  &rfc2119;
  &rfc2606;
  &I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis;
</references>

<references title='Informative References'>
  &rfc1996;
  &rfc5321;
  &rfc5322;
  &rfc7230;
  &rfc7766;
  &rfc7816;
  &rfc8020;
</references> 

</back>

</rfc>



